Marcia Davenport Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Marcia Davenport Papers 1929-1970 (bulk 1932-1960)
MSS17806
Davenport, Marcia, 1903-1996
4,000 items
35 containers
13 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Author and music critic. Correspondence, drafts, galley proofs, typescripts, notes, and press clippings relating to Davenport's books and novels.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Brandt, Carol, 1904-1984--Correspondence.; Cather, Willa, 1873-1947--Correspondence.; Davenport, Marcia, 1903-1996.; Davenport, Marcia, 1903-1996. Constant image. 1960.; Davenport, Marcia, 1903-1996. East side, west side. 1947.; Davenport, Marcia, 1903-1996. Garibaldi; father of modern Italy. 1957.; Davenport, Marcia, 1903-1996. Mozart. 1932.; Davenport, Marcia, 1903-1996. My brother's keeper. 1954.; Davenport, Marcia, 1903-1996. Of Lena Geyer. 1936.; Davenport, Marcia, 1903-1996. Valley of decision. 1942.; Kolodin, Irving, 1908-1988--Correspondence.; Meyer, Wallace--Correspondence.; Moses, Montrose Jonas, 1878-1934--Correspondence.; Perkins, Maxwell E. (Maxwell Evarts), 1884-1947--Correspondence.; Scribner, Charles, 1890-1952--Correspondence.
Subjects
Authors and publishers.
Occupations
Authors.; Music critics.
Provenance
The papers of Marcia Davenport, author and music critic, were deposited in the Library of Congress in 1968 and 1973. The deposits were converted to a gift in 1992.
Additional Guides
The Marcia Davenport Papers are described in Quarterly Journal of the Library of Congress 26, no. 4 (Oct. 1969): 247.
Related Material
A related collection in the Manuscript Division includes the papers of her husband, Russell Wheeler Davenport.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Marcia Davenport are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1903, June 9 Born, New York, N.Y.
1915 1923 Educated at Friends School, Philadelphia, Pa.; Shipley School, Bryn Mawr, Pa.; Wellesley College, Wellesley, Mass.; and received B.A. from Grenoble University, Grenoble, France
1923 Married Frank D. Clarke (divorced 1924)
1924 1928 Advertising copy writer, New York, N.Y.
1928 1931 Editorial staff, The New Yorker
1929 Married Russell W. Davenport (divorced 1946)
1932 Published Mozart. New York, N.Y.: Scribner
1934 1939 Music critic, Stage Magazine
1936 Published Of Lena Geyer. New York, N.Y.: Scribner
1936 1937 Commentator, Metropolitan Opera radio broadcasts
1940 Active in presidential campaign of Wendell L. Willkie
1941 1945 Active in relief work for Czechoslovakia
1942 Published Valley of Decision. New York, N.Y.: Scribner
1945 1948 Lived in Prague, Czechoslovakia
1947 Published East Side, West Side. New York, N.Y.: Scribner
1950 Lived alternately in Europe, chiefly Italy, and New York, N.Y.
1954 Published My Brother's Keeper. New York, N.Y.: Scribner
1957 Published Garibaldi: Father of Modern Italy. New York, N.Y.: Random House
1960 Published The Constant Image. New York, N.Y.: Scribner
1967 Published Too Strong for Fantasy. New York, N.Y.: Scribner
1991 Published Jan Masaryk: Last Portrait. Panorama
1996, Jan. 16 Died, Monterey, Calif.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Marcia Davenport (1903-1996) span the years 1929-1970, with the bulk of the material dating from 1932 to 1960. The papers are mostly in English with a typescript in Czech and are organized into the following series: Correspondence, Literary Manuscripts, and Addition.
The Correspondence largely relates to the preparation and publication of her books and novels and there are numerous drafts and copies of Davenport's outgoing letters. A significant group of correspondence consists of letters from Maxwell E. Perkins, editor-in-chief at Charles Scribner's Sons, from 1931 until his death in 1947. Included among the more than thirty letters from Perkins is a ten-page letter, dated April 28, 1947, concerning revisions of Davenport's novel East Side, West Side. Other correspondents include Carol Brandt, Davenport's literary agent, Charles Scribner, Jr., and Wallace Meyer who succeeded Perkins as Davenport's editor at the Scribner publishing house. There are also individual letters from Willa Cather, Irving Kolodin, and Montrose Jonas Moses. Further correspondence is in the Addition.
The Literary Manuscripts relate to her works published from 1929 to 1960 including Mozart, Of Lena Geyer, Valley of Decision, East Side, West Side, My Brother's Keeper, Garibaldi: Father of Modern Italy, and The Constant Image. Notes and early material relating to her 1967 autobiography Too Strong for Fantasy and the original typescript for My Brother's Keeper are in the Addition. Included with the manuscripts are notes, typescripts, press clippings, typescripts, galley proofs, page proofs, drafts, and fragments.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in three series:
Correspondence, 1929-1959
Literary Manuscripts, 1932-1960
Addition, 1936-1970
Container List
- Correspondence, 1929-1959 (Box 1)
  Incoming and outgoing letters relating to Davenport's publications.
  Arranged into special correspondence of Maxwell E. Perkins and general correspondence.
  - Special correspondence, Maxwell E. Perkins, 1931-1947 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1929-1959, undated (Box 1)
- Literary Manuscripts, 1932-1960 (Box 2-33)
  Drafts, notes, typescripts, galley proofs, page proofs, and press clippings.
  Arranged by title of work and thereunder by type of material.
  - Mozart, 1932 (Box 2)
    - Notes, fragments, and early drafts (Box 2)
    - Fragments of manuscript and typescript (Box 3)
    - Manuscript and typescript (Box 4)
    - Typescript (copy), press clippings, and preface to revised edition (Box 5)
  - Of Lena Geyer, 1936 (Box 6)
    - Early draft manuscript and original manuscript (Box 6)
    - Typescript (copy) and galley proof (fragment) (Box 7)
    - Galley proof (Box 8)
    - Press clippings (Box 9)
  - Valley of Decision, 1942 (Box 10)
    - Research notes, drafts, fragments, and working notes (Box 10)
    - Original manuscript (Box 11)
    - Cuts from original manuscript (Box 12)
    - Revised original manuscript (Box 13)
    - Revised original manuscript (Box 14)
    - Editorial typescript (Box 14)
    - Editorial typescript (Box 15)
    - Galley proof (Box 16)
    - Galley proof (Box 17)
    - Press clippings (Box 18)
    - Press clippings (Box 19)
    - Press clippings (Box 20)
    - Czech translation (typescript) (Box 21)
  - East Side, West Side, 1947 (Box 22)
    - Notes and working material and original manuscript (Box 22)
    - Author's typescript (Box 23)
    - Press clippings (Box 23)
  - My Brother's Keeper, 1954 (Box 24)
    - Working notes, early drafts, and original manuscript (Box 24)
    - Editorial typescript (Box 25)
    - Revised manuscript and page proof (Box 26)
    - Press clippings (Box 27)
  - Garibaldi: Father of Modern Italy, 1957 (Box 28)
    - Notes and original manuscript (Box 28)
    - "So Help Me God," fragment of drama (Box 28)
  - The Constant Image, 1960 (Box 29)
    - Notes and fragments, original manuscript, editorial typescript, and page proof (Box 29)
    - Press clippings (Box 30)
    - Early drafts, fragments, and original manuscript (Box 31)
    - Editorial typescript (Box 32)
    - Galley proof and page proof (Box 33)
- Addition, 1936-1970 (Box 34-35)
  Correspondence, literary manuscripts, clippings, notes, typescripts, and fragments.
  Arranged by type of material or title of work.
  - Correspondence, 1936-1969 (Box 34)
  - Letter to the editor, circa 1947 (Box 34)
  - Notes with clippings, 1967-1968 (Box 34)
  - Clippings (Box 34)
    - Charles Scribner's Sons (Box 34)
    - Literary Clipping Service (Box 34)
    - Clippings and printed matter (Box 34)
  - My Brother's Keeper, original typescript and carbon copy, 1954 (Box 35)
  - Too Strong for Fantasy, rough notes and early material, 1967 (Box 35)
  - Fragments (Box 35)